Hello, class. This is
the next Rapid Farm
concept review question.
We have a
30-year-old female
with a history of
schizophrenia,
and she has a lack of
energy and interest
in her daily life?
The patient has
not experienced
further delusions
or hallucinations,
but is withdrawn from
friends and doesn't
speak to anyone.
She was started
on medication.
At follow up. Several
months later,
she was noted to having
a weight gain
of ten pounds,
an A one C of six
and an LDL of 140.
Which of these
medications was
the most likely cause
of this new presentation?
By now, if you're
looking at the choices,
we know that all of
these are related to
the neuropsych
component which
we covered last spring.
The first answer,
dantrolene,
if we wanted to rule
out an answer off the bat,
that one should
be the one.
Dantrolene is the one that
binds to the
ryanodine receptor,
and if you recall,
that would stop
calcium influx,
from the sarcoma, and
that calcium is
responsible for
muscle contraction.
Where we would
use dantrolene
is in patients that have
malignant hypothermia.
This might be somebody
that has a mutation,
by the way, of the
ryanodine receptor,
and that can happen
after a person has surgery
and maybe was
given anesthesia
with an inhaled
anesthetic.
The other place
for dantrolene
would be a patient
that was taking
a typical ant psychotic
like haloperidol,
flufenazin,
where if they developed
something known
as neuroleptic
malignant syndrome,
they would present with
this high temperature,
and then of course,
they would have
the sustained
muscle contraction
which we refer to as
lead pipe rigidity.
That's a little
different than
serotonin syndrome
because remember
Ceratonin syndrome would
happen with
serotonergic drugs.
There would be some level
of a high temperature,
but the patient would have
myoclonic episodes
that would
not be lead pipe.
Dantrolene would be the
treatment in the case
if the patient had
a NMS presentation.
Haloperidol would
be probably
appropriate if
this patient
was presenting
with delusions,
whether it be
visual or auditory
or if they were
experiencing,
as I just mentioned,
the positive
signs, symptoms
of schizophrenia.
This patient has more
of a negative effect.
We're talking about some
of the negative
presentation,
like they're apathetic,
they're withdrawn
socially.
Most likely she would have
been given an atypical.
Remember, the typicals are
most likely dopinmnurgic
antagonists,
and that would result,
if you recall, if we're
talking about
the nigrosium,
They would have more
mus movement problems.
They would resemble
the Parkinson patient.
They would be rigid,
they would have
brady kinesia.
They may have
enhanced prolactin if
we're talking
about the tuberal
infindibular area.
We can safely say that
it's not he apertol,
the answer in
this question
because the patient
is not experiencing
with the positive signs
of schizophrenia.
Loza Pam would
first of all,
not cause the weight gain
and the change
in metabolics.
Loza pam may
be in the case
if the person was
having perhaps,
anxiety, panic attack, or
if we're thinking about
a patient having seizures.
Remember, Lesa Pam
is a benzodiazepine.
Those are going to
potentiate gaba because of
the increase in chloride
channel opening,
so chloride
channel flows in.
There's going to be
negative charge,
hyperpolarization, and
GABA gets potentiated.
But Lorazapam,
if we were to
worry about some of
the adverse effects,
we might think
about sedation.
We might think about
perhaps abuse potential.
Olanzapine. Thinking about
Olanzapine, remember,
those are the
drugs that fall in
the atypical ant
psychotic class.
Remember, with those,
we are going to
instead of
blocking dopamine
receptors in a strong way.
We're mostly
looking at blocking
the serotonin
two A receptors.
It's probably in
blocking that receptor,
it's almost like
the opposite
of what we would
expect from LSD.
LSD is considered to be
a serotonin two a agonist.
You can try to understand
that patients who have
used LSD get those
type of delusions.
But the idea when we
use the serotonin
blockers,
we're getting a
lot less effect
on the dopamine
two receptor.
We're not going to
have as much going
on with respect
to the movement,
and we're not really
going to have too
much with NMS and
things of that nature.
So One thing to note,
if we were going
to classify,
and I think you saw
the next slide.
If we had to sum it up
in adverse effects with
the antipsychotics,
those that black
dopamine are going to be
more prone to have
movement problems,
higher issues with, for
example, prolactin,
k. But if we were
to give an atypical,
especially Olanzopine.
This is the one that
is going to be most
associated with
the weight gain
and the change
in metabolics.
Patients will start
to experience
this idea of that maybe
they're eating more,
that's number one or an
increase in appetite,
which may be sometimes
a good thing.
But when it gets
to be excessive,
then we run the risk that
their A one C can
go up and that
gives them a high risk
of becoming Type
two diabetic.
Then the LDL story,
where many times
you'll see
that patients
that are taking
something like
Olanzapine are
going to develop
hyperlipidemia,
where we need to
perhaps give a statin,
and we'll be talking about
statins in this lecture.
It comes in a great time.
Before we pick Olanzapine,
which I would say is
in fact the best
answer here.
The last one is srtaln and
Sarteln is considered
to be the SSRI.
Those are going to block
the re uptake
of serotonin,
there'll be more serotonin
present in synaptic clept,
and that means
there'll be more
serotonin binding to
the postsynaptic
receptors.
That will be
something that we
would want with SSRIs,
they're so commonly used
for major depression
disorder,
for post traumatic
stress disorder,
even patients that have
a certain degree of
eating disorders,
even for patients
that have
mood changes during
their menstrual cycle.
Very big group of drugs,
because remember
the SSRIs as
opposed to the
previous group,
the tricyclics, do not
have autonomic
adverse effects.
Because remember,
tricyclics
like amitriptyline,
they are effective
for depression.
But aside from the re
uptake of both cetonin
and nopenprin,
they do have
muscarinic block,
so you're looking at
perhaps the dryness,
maybe the increase
in AV node action.
They may complicate
patients
that have, for example,
glaucoma or even BPH
because of the
urinary retention.
They're alpha
one blockers.
Remember, tricyclics
will cause orthostasis,
and then lastly, they
have histaminic blockade.
That means they will cross
the blood brain barrier
and cause sedation.
Selective serotonin re
uptake inhibitors
don't have that.
They're devoid of those
autonomic effects.
That will be
clear now that
the best answer
in this case
is going to be Olanzapine.
As we move forward,
you probably
already saw the
slide that I was
going to show you
and there we go.
First gen, higher risk
of neurological
side effects.
Here we're talking
about Parkinsonism.
The second
generation, there's
a higher risk of
metabolic side effects.
Again, hyperlipidemia,
hyperglycemia, and of
course, the waking.
Thank you for
your attention.
If you have any
questions on this topic,
please feel free
to let me know,
and I'll definitely
make time to meet with
you and go over some
of these concepts.
But until then,
thank you so
much and have a great
day. Thank you.